A Guide to the Annual Reports of the Archives Division of the Virginia State Library, 1915-1982
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Annual Reports of the Archives Division of the Virginia State Library, 1915-1982
The Library of Virginia
1915-1982
1.92 cubic feet (6 boxes)
Virginia State Archives. Archives Division.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These materials came in three accessions. Included are the following accessions: Acc. 27952, 43276, 43867, & 45034.
Historical Information
For many years, The Library of Virginia had no definitive home. Valuable early records were kept at Jamestown as early as 1676 and were then moved to the College of William and Mary for a brief period at the century's end. By 1780, extant records were moved to the Capitol in Richmond. Coincidentally, in 1779, the Virginia General Assembly was presented among its legislation, "A Bill for Establishing a Public Library" drawn up by Thomas Jefferson. The bill provided for 2000 pounds yearly to be expended to maintain a State Library in Richmond. The facility was to be a reference library only without books being lent for home use. Perhaps ahead of its time, the bill failed to pass.
The Virginia State Library was created by an act passed by the General Assembly on January 23, 1823, to establish a public library with funds derived from the sale of William W. Hening's The Statutes at Large. From 1823 to 1828, the Library was under the control of the governor and council. In 1828, the General Assembly created a joint committee on the library (located in a room in the southeastern corner of the Capitol) to oversee its administration. Use of the State Library was restricted to members of the state government in a policy that continued until at least 1856. The Secretary of the Commonwealth served ex officio as state librarian from 1832 to 1903.
The growth of the State Library was somewhat erratic. Book holdings increased from 1,313 in 1828 to 17,480 in 1856. Lack of funds and politics frequently intermingled to slow library development. General William H. Richardson, State Librarian in 1852, became embroiled in an effort to remove him "to make way for some politician of democratic principles." At the close of Reconstruction, Dr. George William Bagby, then State Librarian, was terminated and his position abolished at the hands of Readjusters. Eventually, on May 15, 1903, the General Assembly passed an act that created a library board to administer the library, authorized the deposit of public records in the library, provided for the publication of historical records by the library, and established a library fund for the purchase of books and private papers. The Library Board, which was responsible for naming the State Librarian, was itself appointed by the Board of Education. The General Assembly passed an act on March 29, 1944, transferring the power to appoint the Library Board to the governor.
While many public records somehow survived the Commonwealth's early years, many losses occurred due to fires, the ravages of war and negligence. When the library was moved, for example, in 1895 to a building separate from the Capitol, "chutes were constructed from the upper story of the Capitol to facilitate the delivery of books to the wagons of the junk dealer who had bought them." The move was poorly planned and the library's contents suffered great loss at the hands of those very authorities assigned to protect them.
The new facility quickly was found to be inadequate and efforts were made both in 1910 and 1920 to construct a proper building for the State Library and its collections. Ground was broken for the current facility on December 7, 1938. At last, on December 23, 1940, the newly completed Virginia State Library was opened to the public.
The Virginia State Library adopted the name, the Virginia State Library and Archives, in early 1987 to more adequately reflect its mission and purpose today. In July 1, 1994 the name was changed to The Library of Virginia.
Scope and Content
The Annual Reports of the Archives Division are housed in five archival boxes and are arranged chronologically. This collection documents the work of the Archives Division of the Virginia State Library between 1915 and 1976.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Annual Reports of the Archives Division of the Virginia State Library, 1915-1982.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Location of Originals
Original annual reports between 1915 and 1936 and located among the Morgan P. Robinson Papers at the Virginia Historical Society.
Contents List
- Annual Reports of the Archives Division of the Virginia State Library, 1915-1982., Extent: 1.92
  This collection contains printed, typescript, and handwritten draft copies of the annual reports of the Archives Division of the Virginia State Library between 1915 & 1976. The earliest annual reports, 1915-1936, consist of typescript annual reports compiled by Morgan P. Robinson, the first State Archivist of the Virginia State Library. These early annual reports were photocopied from the Morgan P. Robinson Papers at the Virginia Historical Society. Robinson submitted his reports to Henry R. McIlwaine, State Librarian. The reports were then submitted to the State Library Board for review. The reports contain financial information, as well as notes about collections processing and utilization, and other issues involving the archives department. In addition, the Annual Reports convey information regarding attendance & use statistics, shelving, conservation, the Photographic Laboratory, staffing, acquisitions, a new state library building, Photostat Division, W.J. Barrow's restoration, classification & cataloguing of manuscript collections, microfilming, outreach activities, exhibits, publications, purchases, binding, the Virginia Colonial Records Project, the Virginia Civil War Commission, the Virginia Bicentennial Commission, request for & authorization of records retirement (lists agency & number of requests), and reference. Beginning in 1940 through 1969, the files include a copy of the published annual report of the Virginia State Library. Morgan P. Robinson was succeeded as State Archivist by William J. Van Schreeven in 1939 who served in that capacity until 1969. Louis H. Manarin in turn succeeded Van Schreeven in 1969. The reports of the Archives Division beginning in 1972 include reports of John W. Dudley, Head of the Archives Branch; Connis O. Brown, Head of the Local Records Branch; Patricia Hicklin, Head of the Publications Branch; and Col. Howard MacCord, Archeologist.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1915-1916 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1917-1919 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1920-1921 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1923-1924 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1927 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1933-1936 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1938 July 1-1939 June 30 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1939 July 1-1940 June 30 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 1940 July 1-1941 June 30 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 1941 July 1-1942 June 30 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1942 July 1-1943 June 30 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1943 July 1-1944 June 30 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 1944 July 1-1945 June 30 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 1945 July 1-1946 June 30 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - 1946 July 1-1947 June 30 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 1947 July 1-1948 June 30 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 1948 July 1-1949 June 30 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 1949 July 1-1950 June 30 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 1950 July 1-1951 June 30 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - 1950 July 1-1951 June 30 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1952 July 1-1953 June 30 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1953 July 1-1954 June 30 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 1954 July 1-1955 June 30 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 1955 July 1-1956 June 30 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 1956 July 1-1957 June 30 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 1957 July 1-1958 June 30 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - 1958 July 1-1959 June 30 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - 1959 July 1-1960 June 30 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - 1960 July 1-1961 June 30 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - 1961 July 1-1962 June 30 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - 1962 July 1-1963 June 30 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - 1963 July 1-1964 June 30 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - 1964 July 1-1965 June 30 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - 1965 July 1-1966 June 30 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - 1966 July 1-1967 June 30 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - 1967 July 1-1968 June 30 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - 1968 July 1-1969 June 30 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - 1969 July 1-1970 June 30 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - 1970 July 1-1971 June 30 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - 1971 July 1-1972 June 30 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - 1972 July 1-1973 June 30 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - 1973 July 1-1974 June 30 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - 1974 July 1-1975 June 30 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - 1975 July 1-1976 June 30 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - 1976 July 1-1977 June 30 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - 1977 July 1-1978 June 30 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - 1978 July 1-1979 June 30 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - 1979 July 1-1980 June 30 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - 1980-1981 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - 1981-1982 (Box 6, Folder 2)